<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Chris Allum Portfolio</title>
    <link>https://chrisallum.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Chris Allum Portfolio</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://chrisallum.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Lab Engineer at Brandeis University</title>
      <link>https://chrisallum.com/scope/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisallum.com/scope/</guid>
      <description>Summary  Worked with Brandeis University to redesign a piece of laboratory equipment called the Flybox from scratch Wrote firmware in C on an ESP32 to create new user interface and underlying controls for device Wrote code to deserialize, parse, and manipulate JSON text files Wrote code to integrate control of optogenetic lights, RTC chips, LCD display, buttons, and other peripherals Worked with Brandeis research lab for user testing through multiple iterations and design changes  Scope Summit Poster  About For my senior capstone project at Olin College, I worked with a team with Olin students in collaboration with Brandeis University to redesign a piece of laboratory equipment called the FlyBox.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Markforged Software Intern</title>
      <link>https://chrisallum.com/markforged/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisallum.com/markforged/</guid>
      <description> Summary  Software intern working on user interface and functionality of new FX20 3D printers Wrote internal benchmarking and stress testing tools used to test print file parsing and decryption Wrote internal software optimizations that reduced print file processing time by around 7x Wrote event logging functionality to help developers understand the current state of the machine and to make debugging and finding errors easier Worked on miscellaneous bug fixes and small upgrades Worked primarily in Typescript and a tiny bit with Rust Participated daily standup meetings  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Robotics Research at Boston University</title>
      <link>https://chrisallum.com/bu_robotics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisallum.com/bu_robotics/</guid>
      <description>About I am current working at BU as a Robotics Research Intern under Professor Tron in conjunction with PhD candidate Zili Wang in the BU Robotics Lab.
 Weekly Log I&amp;rsquo;m keeping a weekly log of things that I got done and things that I learned as well as any interesting results.
June 3 - 7  For this week, I mainly spent time getting familiar with the project background as well as getting onboarded with everything.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Baja SAE</title>
      <link>https://chrisallum.com/baja/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisallum.com/baja/</guid>
      <description>Summary  Suspension design lead for 3 years Led a team of 10 members in designing a new four-wheel drive suspension system for a competitive off-road vehicle Organized and led bi-weekly suspension team meetings Mentored students in topics such as design for manufacturing, failure analysis, and FEA Designed front suspension geometry, brakes, and steering assemblies  By the numbers  50+ custom designed vehicle components 300+ hours in the machine shop 100+ parts machined (Lathe, Mill, CNC Mill, Welded)  Photo Gallary Below are a bunch of photos of parts that I have designed or made:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Custom 3D Printer Slicer for Fiber Reinforced Prints</title>
      <link>https://chrisallum.com/3d_slicer/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisallum.com/3d_slicer/</guid>
      <description>Summary  Created a custom 3d printer slicer that takes any 3d model and slices it into a set of paths that are optimized for fiber inlays. Each layer is a single stroke and non self-intersecting Custom infill geometry (square, triangle, or hexagon) and infill density  Context Inspired by the following research paper:
 A novel single-stroke path planning algorithm for 3D printers using continuous carbon fiber reinforced thermoplastics - Yamamoto et al.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Honda Robotics Internship</title>
      <link>https://chrisallum.com/honda/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisallum.com/honda/</guid>
      <description>Summary  Worked as a robotics intern at Honda Manufacturing Alabama Automotive Plant in the robotic welding division Helped install and train a vision system on a Fanuc spot welding robot to assist in pick and place operations Reduced mispicks led to a reduction in assembly line downtime, costs, and human injury Worked to install and train a vision system to gather data on another Fanuc pick and place robot. Data was used to identify potential problems with line operations and identify source of inconsistent robot operations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warehouse Robotics Obstacle Avoidance</title>
      <link>https://chrisallum.com/samiam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisallum.com/samiam/</guid>
      <description>Summary  Developed a novel method of obstacle avoidance for warehouse robotics using and overhead RGB camera Used camera to detect potential obstacles using real-time image segmentation Used Control Lyapnuov Functions - Control Barrier Functions (CLF-CBF) to create a local path planner to re-route robot around potential obstacles Used differential drive robot kinematics and inverse-kinematics to control robot along path  Context For my class EK505: Introduction to Robotics, for our final project, my team designed an obstacle avoidance system for warehouse robots.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>B-trees</title>
      <link>https://chrisallum.com/b-tree/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisallum.com/b-tree/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Design for Manufacturing</title>
      <link>https://chrisallum.com/dfm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisallum.com/dfm/</guid>
      <description>Summary  Designed and fabricated series of objects from scratch using DFM principles Used techniques such as CNC milling, vacuum forming, injection molding, silicon molding, and more  Treasure Box The first project that I worked on was designing a &amp;ldquo;treasure box&amp;rdquo; that would be machined out of a 6&amp;quot;x6&amp;quot;x3&amp;quot; block of aluminum. The box would be CNC milled using a Tormach mill. I decided that I would try to make my box look like a pie.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics Simulations</title>
      <link>https://chrisallum.com/dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisallum.com/dynamics/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Path Planning for Robot Vacuum using Gradient Descent</title>
      <link>https://chrisallum.com/neato/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisallum.com/neato/</guid>
      <description>About  
In this project, I programed a Neato vacuuming robot to traverse an obstacle course. The Neato was placed in an arena with several boxes that served as obstacles. The goal was for the Neato to autonomously scan the environment using it&amp;rsquo;s LIDAR sensor, plan a course (avoiding the obstacles), and make its way to the goal object, a round barrel.
 Above is an image of the course the robot was placed in.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rock Paper Scissors CNN Machine Learning Model</title>
      <link>https://chrisallum.com/rock_paper_scissors/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisallum.com/rock_paper_scissors/</guid>
      <description>In this project, I built a CNN machine learning model to identify hand poses in a game of rock paper scissors using PyTorch.
 Final Report  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wheeled Inverted Pendulum Robot Using PID Control System</title>
      <link>https://chrisallum.com/rocky/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisallum.com/rocky/</guid>
      <description>In this project, I helped design and implement a control system that maintains the balance of a wheeled inverted pendulum and corrects for angular disturbance.
For this project, we used a Pololu Balboa 32U4 robot kit as the robotic base with a set of 0.6 m long laser-cut MDF side extension to raise the center of mass and create the inverted pendulum. At the top of the robot are a set of weights, adding up to around 200g.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>High School Robotics</title>
      <link>https://chrisallum.com/hs_robotics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisallum.com/hs_robotics/</guid>
      <description>I was the head of my HS robotics team during my Junior and Senior years. We competed in the MATE ROV competition were we had to build an underwater remotely operated vehicle (ROV) to preform a series of tasks. Here are a few images of the robots I helped build and design.
Our Rover These are photos of our final robot. The internals of the robot contained six motor controllers, an Arduino, and a Raspberry Pi.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Object Recognition: Hot Dog or Not</title>
      <link>https://chrisallum.com/object_recognition/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisallum.com/object_recognition/</guid>
      <description>About In this project, I created an algorithm that attempted to identify whether an image was a hot dog or not.
To build this algorithm, I first assembled a training set of 89 images of hot dogs. I then removed the background noise in each photo and re-oriented the hot dog so that it lay horizontal across the center of a 72x128 frame. I then vectorized each photo into a 9216x1x3 matrix (one column vector for each set of RGB value.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Python Platformer Game</title>
      <link>https://chrisallum.com/game_development/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisallum.com/game_development/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Waypoint Navigation Rover</title>
      <link>https://chrisallum.com/rover/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisallum.com/rover/</guid>
      <description>Overview With a team of 5 other Olin students, I helped built a fully autonomous rover that was capable of driving around campus. The Rover was capable of driving from point to point while preforming obstacle avoidance. The Rover also had a manipulator on the front that was capable of picking up and dropping items.
The rover navigated using a series of sensors. On the rover were two sonar sensors, five infrared distance sensors, a GPS module, and webcam capable of object recognition.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bio Inspired Hopper</title>
      <link>https://chrisallum.com/hopper/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisallum.com/hopper/</guid>
      <description>For this project, I designed a &amp;ldquo;hopper&amp;rdquo; using a set of limited materials. The aim of this project was to learn more about design process, using CAD, and prototyping.
This was the first drawing of my hopper. I really wanted to incorporate a four-bar linkage as the primary jumping mechanism. I was also inspired by a how a grasshopper shoots it&amp;rsquo;s leg out to jump. These sources of inspiration are what lead me to this design.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
